Isabel Leighton Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Isabel Leighton papers
1890-1984
1922-1984
YCAL MSS 766
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
11.51
(35 boxes) + 1 art object
The Isabel Leighton Papers contain writings, correspondence, personal papers, audiovisual material, photographs, and printed material that document her career as an actress, playwright, journalist, screenwriter, and civic activist, promoting public measures to improve mental health. Writings include typescript drafts, many with minor revisions, for works including "The Sapphire Ring," "Katja," and "Mercenary Mary." Correspondence, while not extensive, includes files on theatrical projects such as "Spring Again," and files relating to her work as a naval correspondent in Asia during the Second World War. The scrapbooks document Leighton's theatrical performances in the 1930s, journalism in the 1940s, and broadcast production in the 1950s and 1960s. Photographs largely feature Leighton, though also include images of colleagues, acquaintances, and family members.
Leighton, Isabel
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Bequest of Isabel Leighton, 1996.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Box 30 (Record Album Storage) and boxes 34-36 (16mm film): Restricted fragile material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
Boxes 27-29, 31 (Record Album Storage): Use of originals is restricted. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
Isabel Leighton (1901-1995)
Isabel Leighton, American actress, author, foreign correspondent, and civic activist, was born July 17, 1901 and died April 22, 1995. During her lengthy and diverse career she authored novels, plays, and magazine articles, was an associate editor of Vogue magazine, served as a naval correspondent in Asia during the Second World War, and promoted mental health through public outreach and education. Leighton was married twice: to Frederic A. Willis, and to Arthur Hugh Bunker (Yale 1915, d. 1963).
Scope and Contents
The Isabel Leighton Papers contain writings, correspondence, personal papers, audiovisual material, photographs, and printed material that document her career as an actress, playwright, journalist, screenwriter, and civic activist, promoting public measures to improve mental health. Writings include typescript drafts, many with minor revisions, for works including "The Sapphire Ring," "Katja," and "Mercenary Mary." Correspondence, while not extensive, includes files on theatrical projects such as "Spring Again," and files relating to her work as a naval correspondent in Asia during the Second World War. The scrapbooks document Leighton's theatrical performances in the 1930s, journalism in the 1940s, and broadcast production in the 1950s and 1960s. Photographs largely feature Leighton, though also include images of colleagues, acquaintances, and family members.
Arrangement
Organized into seven series: I. Writings, 1922-1980. II. Correspondence, 1931-1982. III. Photographs, circa 1890-1962. IV. Personal and Financial Papers, 1923-1984. V. Printed Material, 1922-1978. VI. Collages and Scrapbooks, 1922-1965. VII. Audiovisual Material, 1943-1964.
Actors -- United States; Journalists -- United States; Authors, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Mental health -- United States; Radio plays -- Production and direction; Television -- Production and direction; Theater -- United States; War correspondents -- United States; Women war correspondents -- United States; World War, 1939-1945 -- Journalists; Audiovisual materials; Audiotapes -- United States -- 20th Century; Motion pictures (visual works) -- United States -- 20th Century; Photographs -- United States -- 20th Century; Scrapbooks -- United States -- 20th Century; Scripts (documents) -- United States -- 20th Century; Television scripts -- United States -- 20th Century; Actors -- United States -- 20th Century; Authors -- United States -- 20th Century; Journalists -- United States -- 20th Century; War correspondents -- United States -- 20th Century; Leighton, Isabel
- Writings, 1922-1980; Series I; 2.71; (7 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  The Writings series consists chiefly of typescript drafts (some corrected) of works by Isabel Leighton, including playscripts, telescripts, radio scripts, speeches, and essays. Some files include correspondence and other related material.
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically by title. Unidentified works are filed at the end.
  - "About Face, Face Value, The Pathfinder", undated (Box 1)
  - "America in the Saddle", undated (Box 1)
  - "American Beauty", 1970; 3 (Box 1)
  - "Anchors Away", undated (Box 1)
  - "Ant Samantha", undated (Box 1)
  - "Broadway Pilgrims", undated; 2 (Box 1)
  - "Chaplain of the Deep", undated (Box 1)
  - "Children's Court", undated (Box 1)
  - "The Christmas Seal", undated (Box 1)
  - "Citizen of the World", undated (Box 1)
  - "Confuse 'em and Use 'em", undated (Box 2)
  - "The Consumer and the N.R.A.", 1934 (Box 2)
  - "Crown of Nettles", 1970 (Box 2)
  - "The Dagger and the Rose", undated (Box 2)
  - "Danger Ahead", undated (Box 2)
  - "Days of Decision", 1970-1980; 2 (Box 2)
  - "The Debutante Racket", undated (Box 2)
  - "Double Play", undated (Box 2)
  - "Dressmaker's Story", 1940, undated; 4 (Box 2)
  - "Express to the Stars", 1940; 2 (Box 3)
  - "Fat Lady", undated (Box 3)
  - "Fight for Your Lady", undated (Box 3)
  - "The First Lady of the Land", undated (Box 3)
  - "The General Nobody Knows", undated (Box 3)
  - "The Good Listener", undated (Box 3)
  - "Good Night, Pleasant Dreams, God Bless You", undated (Box 3)
  - "Gulf Stream", undated (Box 3)
  - "Harry Content", undated (Box 3)
  - "Home Sweet Home", undated (Box 3)
  - "Honey Bear Goes to the Fair", undated; 2 (Box 3)
  - "How Did They Get That Way?", 1951-1966; 4 (Box 3)
  - "Humanity's Traveling Salesman", undated (Box 3)
  - "Hypnosis is not a Parlour Game", undated (Box 3)
  - "I Met Mr. Justice Holmes", undated (Box 4)
  - "The Inconsistent Moon", undated (Box 4)
  - "Indian Operetta", undated (Box 4)
  - "Indian Summer", undated (Box 4)
  - "Katja the Dancer", undated (Box 4)
  - "Lombard Story", 1937 (Box 4)
  - "The Lonely Road", undated (Box 4)
  - "The Love Chase", 1922 (Box 4)
  - "Love for the Taking", undated (Box 4)
  - "Lucky Penny", 1940 (Box 4)
  - "Interview with Madam Chang Kai Chek", circa 1945 (Box 4)
  - "Marie-Adelaide", 1941 (Box 4)
  - "Mary Jane Romps Home", undated (Box 5)
  - "Men Are Like That", undated (Box 5)
  - "Men Have Been Shot for Less", undated (Box 5)
  - "Mercenary Mary", undated (Box 5)
  - "The Miracle is Love", circa 1950 (Box 5)
  - "Miss Higgins Sees Life Through", undated (Box 5)
  - "A Modern Look at the Ten Commandments", undated (Box 5)
  - "The Morning After", 1922 (Box 5)
  - "The Most Discussed Woman in America (Alice Longworth)", 1930 (Box 5)
  - "New York Heart-Beat", undated (Box 5)
  - "Odyssey to Freedom", 1944 (Box 5)
  - "Russia Plays Blind Man's Bluff", undated (Box 5)
  - "The Sapphire Ring", undated (Box 5)
  - "The Scarlet Cockatoo", undated (Box 6)
  - "Shortcut to Tokyo", undated (Box 6)
  - "Spring Again", undated (Box 6)
  - "Stage Door Canteen", 1942; 2 (Box 6)
  - "Strong Men are Weak", undated (Box 6)
  - "Success Story: U.S.A.", undated (Box 6)
  - "Time Out For Love", 1937 (Box 6)
  - "Tomorrow", 1923 (Box 6)
  - "Tonnage Finds Wings", undated (Box 6)
  - "Travel", undated (Box 6)
  - "Tycoon", undated (Box 6)
  - "Wanderlust Anyone?", undated (Box 6)
  - "Wayward Bound", 1936 (Box 6)
  - "We Only Live Once", 1936 (Box 6)
  - "When Love was King", undated (Box 6)
  - "Womans Club", 1946; 2 (Box 6)
  - "Women's Rally Speech, Consumer's Drive", 1933 August 28 (Box 7)
  - "Literary miscellaneous", undated (Box 7)
  - Untitled Comedy, undated; 4 (Box 7)
  - Untitled, undated; 3 (Box 7)
- Correspondence, 1931-1982; Series II; 0.83; (2 boxes)
  Organized into files by topic; files are not arranged in any particular order.
  Series II consists of professional correspondence and letters of introduction relating to Leighton's service as an accredited war correspondent throughout Asia during the Second World War, and her research on the USS Marblehead; her resignation as Chairman of the Women's Division of the National Recovery Administration in 1933; and to other of Leighton's writings.
  - War Correspondent, 1945-1946; 2 (Box 8)
  - Letters of introduction, 1945 (Box 8)
  - Marblehead Men, 1943-1944; 3 (Box 8)
  - My Boy Franklin, 1933-1945 (Box 8)
  - National Recovery Administration, 1933; 2 (Box 8)
  - Swing, Raymond Gram, 1934-1939 (Box 8)
  - Who's Who in America, 1933-1945 (Box 9)
  - The Aspirin Age, 1931-1962 (Box 9)
  - Marie-Adelaide, 1941 (Box 9)
  - Unsorted, 1931-1982; 8 (Box 9)
- Photographs, circa 1890-1962; Series III; 0.75; (2 boxes)
  Photographs are chiefly of Isabel Leighton, dating from the 1920s to the 1960s, and include studio portraits and snapshots that document Leighton's career as an actress and journalist, as well as her civic activism. Also included are family photographs, the earliest of which dates to circa 1890.
  - Photographs, circa 1890-1962; 43 (Box 10)
  - Photographs, 1920s-1950s; 8 (Box 11 (Oversize))
  - Photographs of Isabel Leighton as a child, framed, circa 1901-1915 (Box 12 (Oversize))
- Personal and Financial Papers, 1923-1984; Series IV; 0.63; (2 boxes) + 1 folder
  - Curriculum vitae, undated (Box 13)
  - Passports, 1945-1971 (Box 13)
  - Membership cards, 1952-1954 (Box 13)
  - War Department identification card, 1945 (Box 13)
  - Contracts, agreements and memos, 1923-1970; 6 (Box 13)
  - Financial papers, 1943-1958; 2 (Box 13)
  - Spring Again, financial papers, 1943-1957 (Box 13)
  - Distinguished Citizen Award, 1958 (Box 14)
  - Founders certificate, undated (Box 14)
  - Kennel Club, 1959 (Box 14)
  - Other papers, 1947-1974 (Box 14)
  - Arthur Bunker obituary and other papers, 1967, undated (Box 14)
  - Youth Counseling League donation receipt, 1984 (Box 14)
  - Mental health activism, papers and programs, 1942-1951; 3 (Box 14)
  - Drawing of Isabel Leighton by Christos Simatos (Box 17 (Oversize))
- Printed Material, 1922-1978; Series V; 1.33; (4 boxes)
  - Sheet music, 1922-1927 (Box 15)
  - Brochures and programs, 1941-1967; 2 (Box 15)
  - Magazines, 1931-1978; 7 (Box 15)
  - Magazines, 1929-1969; 7 (Box 16)
  - Clippings, 1931-1966; 6 (Box 16)
  - Clippings, 1932-1964; 2 (Box 17 (Oversize))
  - New Yorker advertisement, 1949 (Box 17 (Oversize))
  - Saturday Evening Post, 1943 (Box 17 (Oversize))
  - Dust jackets, undated (Box 18 (Oversize))
- Collages and Scrapbooks, 1922-1965; Series VI; 1.42; (8 boxes) + 1 art object
  Clippings, photographs, and ephemera that document Isabel Leighton's creative and civic activities.
  Organized into two subseries: Collages and Scrapbooks.
  - Collages
    - National Recovery Administration, 1933 (Box 18 (Oversize))
    - Arthur Bunker / Saint Luke's Hospital, 1965 (Box 18 (Oversize))
    - "Cavalcade of America" radio programs, 1943-1944 (Box 18 (Oversize))
    - Department of Labor Hearings, 81st Congress, 1951; 2 (Box 18 (Oversize))
    - Prince of Luxemburg, 1941 (Box 18 (Oversize))
    - Public appearances, circa 1947 (Box 19 (Oversize))
    - Collage, framed, undated (Box 20 (Art))
  - Scrapbooks
    - Scrapbook, 1926-1937 (Box 21 (Oversize))
    - Clippings removed from scrapbook, 1926-1937; 2 (Box 21 (Oversize))
    - "Spring Again", 1941-1942 (Box 22 (Oversize))
    - NRA Drive, 1933 (Box 23 (Oversize))
    - Theater, 1922-1926 (Box 24)
    - "Is This Your Problem?", 1951-1952 (Box 25 (Oversize))
    - Television, 1951-1952 (Box 25 (Oversize))
    - Vogue, 1930s (Box 25 (Oversize))
    - Scrapbook, circa 1920-1950 (Box 26 (Oversize))
- Audiovisual Material, 1943-1964; Series VII; 3.84; (10 boxes)
  Conditions Governing Access
  Box 30 (Record album storage) and boxes 34-36 (16mm film): Restricted fragile material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
  Boxes 27-29, 31 (Record album storage): Use of originals is restricted. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
  Organized into two subseries: Phonograph Records, and Films.
  - Phonograph Records
    - Rudolph the Red Nosed Reindeer/The Teddy Bear Picnic Decca recording, undated; (1 10" disc) (Box 27 (Record album storage))
    - "Isabel Leighton, interviewed by Frank Hogan, McCall's Magazine," Parts 1 - 2, undated; (2 12" discs) (Box 27 (Record album storage))
    - "Musical Cheers, the Isabel Leighton Show," Re-recorded from client tape, Empire Broadcasting, undated; (3 12" discs) (Box 27 (Record album storage))
    - "A. L. Alexander Meditation Board," WOR, Rockhill Recording, 1948 December 12; (3 12" discs) (Box 27 (Record album storage))
    - "A. L. Alexander Meditation Board," WOR Recording, 1948 December 12; (3 12" discs) (Box 27 (Record album storage))
    - "A. L. Alexander Meditation Board," Empire Broadcasting, 1949 January 30; (4 12" discs) (Box 27 (Record album storage))
    - "A. L. Alexander Meditation Board," WOR recording, 1949 June 19; (3 12" discs) (Box 27 (Record album storage))
    - "Books on Trial, The Aspirin Age," MGM Recording Studio, undated; (5 12" discs) (Box 28 (Record album storage))
    - "Your Better Tomorrow: Anxiety," Isabel Leighton, American Broadcasting Company, 1956 Janurary 25; (1 12" disc) (Box 28 (Record album storage))
    - "Your Better Tomorrow: What Love Is/What Love is Not," Isabel Leighton, American Broadcasting Company, 1956 January 25; (1 12" disc) (Box 28 (Record album storage))
    - "Your Better Tomorrow: Popularity/Ambition," Isabel Leighton, American Broadcasting Company, 1956 January 25; (1 12" disc) (Box 28 (Record album storage))
    - "How Did They Get That Way?" Isabel Leighton and Dr. Robert Knight, WJZ-TV, part 2, Presto Recording Company, undated; (1 12" disc) (Box 28 (Record album storage))
    - "Woman's Club, CBS Line," Empire Broadcasting, 1946 July 10; (2 12" discs) (Box 28 (Record album storage))
    - "Woman's Club, Marquis Child," Empire Broadcasting, 1946 June 24; (2 12" discs) (Box 28 (Record album storage))
    - "Woman's Club, Dr. Barbara Biber, Bank Street School," Empire Broadcasting, 1946 June 27; (2 12" discs) (Box 28 (Record album storage))
    - "Woman's Club, John Tasker [Harvard] and Bennett Art Programs," Empire Broadcasting, 1946 June 18; (2 12" discs) (Box 28 (Record album storage))
    - "Woman's Club, Louis Untermeyer Show," Empire Broadcasting, 1946 July 9; (2 12" discs) (Box 28 (Record album storage))
    - "Woman's Club, with Robert Parsons," WABC, Associated Recording studios, 1946 June 11; (2 12" discs) (Box 29 (Record album storage))
    - "Woman's Club, with Bennett Cerf," Empire Broadcasting, 1946 June 5; (2 12" discs) (Box 29 (Record album storage))
    - "Woman's Club, The Laurence Frank Show," Columbia Reference Recording, Columbia Broadcast Company, 1946 May 16; (2 12" discs) (Box 29 (Record album storage))
    - "Woman's Club, Doctor Laurette Bender Show," Empire Broadcasting, 1946 July 11; (2 12" discs) (Box 29 (Record album storage))
    - "Dorothy and Dick," WOR, Advertisers Recording Service, 1945 June 19; (2 12" discs) (Box 29 (Record album storage))
    - "When Strangers Meet," American Broadcasting Company, 1954 February 25; (2 12" discs) (Box 29 (Record album storage))
    - "Tex and Jinx Show," Isabel Leighton, guest, Reference Recording, National Broadcasting Company, 1949 October 27; (2 12" discs) (Box 29 (Record album storage))
    - "Cavalcade of America," Reference Recording, National Broadcasting Company, 1943 August 9; (3 12" discs) (Box 30 (Record album storage))
      "Shortcut to Tokyo," penned on packaging envelope. Side 2/5 broken.
      30 (Record Album Storage): Restricted fragile material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
    - "Cavalcade of America," Reference Recording, National Broadcasting Company, 1943 May 10; (3 12" discs) (Box 30 (Record album storage))
    - "When Strangers Meet," re-recorded, Empire Broadcasting, 1954 January 8; (2 16" discs) (Box 31 (Record album storage))
    - "When Strangers Meet, audition," American Broadcasting Company, 1954 February 15; (1 16" disc) (Box 31 (Record album storage))
    - "Musical Cheers, the Isabel Leighton Show," Empire Broadcasting, undated; (2 16" discs) (Box 31 (Record album storage))
    - "Martha Dean, Isabel Leighton for rebroadcast," WOR, 1950 January 20; (3 16" discs) (Box 31 (Record album storage))
    - "Woman's Club audition, Isabel Leighton," Columbia Broadcasting Company, 1946 April 29; (1 16" disc) (Box 31 (Record album storage))
    - Associated mailing envelopes
      - Isabel Leighton, interviewed by Frank Hogan, McCall's Magazine", undated (Box 32 (Oversize))
      - "Musical Cheers,"Isabel Leighton Show, Empire Broadcasting Corporation, undated (Box 32 (Oversize))
      - "A. L. Alexander's Meditation Board", 1948-1949; 2 (Box 32 (Oversize))
      - "Books on Trial, The Aspirin Age," MGM Recording Studio, undated (Box 32 (Oversize))
      - "Your Better Tomorrow," Isabel Leighton, American Broadcasting Company, 1956 (Box 32 (Oversize))
      - "Woman's Club, CBS Line," Empire Broadcasting, 1946 (Box 32 (Oversize))
      - "Cavalcade of America, Shortcut to Tokyo," National Broadcasting Company, 1943 (Box 32 (Oversize))
      - "Cavalcade of America, [?] Girl", 1943 (Box 32 (Oversize))
      - "Woman's Club," Marquis Child, Empire Broadcasting Corporation, 1946 (Box 32 (Oversize))
      - "Woman's Club," Dr. Barbara Biber, Bank Street School, Empire Broadcast, 1946 (Box 32 (Oversize))
      - "Woman's Club, John Tasker", 1946 (Box 32 (Oversize))
      - "Woman's Club, Louis Untermeyer", 1946 (Box 32 (Oversize))
      - "Woman's Club, Laurence Frank Show", 1946 (Box 32 (Oversize))
      - "Woman's Club, Doctor Laurette Bender", 1946 (Box 32 (Oversize))
      - "How Did They Get That Way?", undated (Box 32 (Oversize))
      - "When Strangers Meet", 1954; 2 (Box 33 (Oversize))
      - "Musical Cheers," rerecorded for client, Empire Broadcast Corporation, undated (Box 33 (Oversize))
      - "Woman's Club," Columbia Recording Company, 1946 (Box 33 (Oversize))
  - Films
    Boxes 34-36 (16mm film): Restricted fragile material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
    - "How Did They Get This Way?" American Broadcasting Company TV Productions, 1952 March 6; (1 16mm reel) (Box 34 (Restricted Fragile))
    - "How Did They Get This Way?" American Broadcasting Company Productions, 1951-1952; (2 16mm reels) (Box 35 (Restricted Fragile))
    - "How Did They Get This Way?" American Broadcasting Company Productions, 1951-1952; (2 16mm reels) (Box 36 (Restricted Fragile))